Mr Bewg's Reference

Dear Mr Corncrake

Re: Mr B Bewg, 164 Dismal Terrace, Hoon

Thank you for your letter of 14 July regarding the above-named. I am happy to provide him with a reference.

I have known Mr Bewg for ten years, ever since he took up the position of scrivener, dogsbody and wretch in my vast gloomy factory perched on the hillside next to the lunatic asylum. At the time I engaged Mr Bewg I suspected that he had some past connection with the latter institution, and in the decade since I have had no reason to revise my opinion.

You ask me to comment on my impression of Mr Bewg's “suitability for the job”. Forgive me if I find this difficult. I do not wish to do violence to our mother tongue, but to use the word “suitability” in conjunction with Mr Bewg is to mock the Queen's English. Indeed, it is to make a mockery of Sense itself.

My problems with Mr Bewg began on his very first morning in my employ. To settle him in, I had instructed him to carry out a menial task, removing bits of goo from the interior walls of a vat. To facilitate his progress, he was supplied with a variety of tools including a pencil sharpener, a pin-cushion, and a decidedly ferocious blowtorch. No sooner had I turned my back than Mr Bewg became embroiled in a tussle with my pet panther, which—crazed with hunger—managed to slip its leash and embed its razor-sharp fangs in his left leg. For this impertinence I had no option but to dock Mr Bewg his first month's wages.

It was not a good start, but I had had many a ne'er-do-well working for me in the past, and believed that I could yet mould Mr Bewg into a marginally less repellent specimen of human dregs. To this end, I assigned him to work in the filthiest, dankest wing of the factory, where he was expected to spend all day dragging sacks full of huge iron lumps backwards and forwards through infested tunnels for no apparent purpose. So ineptly did Mr Bewg execute his duties that I was forced to withhold his pay for a further year. I wrung my hands with frustration, but the man was impossible. Given a simple task, he was utterly incapable of completing it with the requisite speed, good humour and fawning obeisance that one expects.

To give just one example: Mr Bewg failed to budge one particularly heavy sack (containing a score of medium-sized anvils) a single inch, despite being given all of four and a half minutes to drag it eight hundred yards along a stinking tunnel in which small bonfires of sulphur had been ignited only moments before. I set a wolfhound yapping at his heels, but to no avail. The man was purely and simply workshy. But I am a fair man, and I had no wish to consign him irrevocably into the underclass of the unemployed and unemployable.

Instead, I agreed with Mr Bewg that he could embark upon a training scheme. In return for a modest fee to be paid to me daily, in cash, I offered to provide him with a comprehensive course of training in a multiplicity of disciplines, both within the factory and in the adjoining administrative hellhole. In the first week alone, we covered a huge range of skills: licking my boots till they gleamed, prostrating himself on his stomach whenever I came within two hundred yards of him, and slobbering with happiness at the mere mention of my name.

At this stage in what can only roughly be called his “career”, Mr Bewg crawled into my palatial office one day to request my assistance with a personal matter. Tempted though I was to have him savaged by giant badgers, I reclined in my unbelievably comfortable executive armchair and heard him out. He confessed that he was in some financial difficulties and begged me to help. Sipping my glass of ruinously expensive wine, I delivered a stern lecture on the virtues of thrift and idly beat him about the skull with a copy of Self-Help. I admitted that I was in a position to pay his paltry debts a billionfold if I wished to, but that such a course of action would not in the long run be of the slightest benefit to him. I then advised him that he could earn a few extra pounds by selling various of his bodily organs and thus better his financial situation while basking in the knowledge that he was being self-reliant rather than coming cap-in-hand to his employer. To prove my point, I offered to buy one of his kidneys and two pints of his blood on the spot, for which I would pay him fourpence. As the bulk of his debts were monies owed to me, I generously docked the fourpence from his account. In this way, I was able to relieve him of the responsibility of handling any cash himself, and thereby falling prey to the inevitable temptation to fritter the money away on food, clothing, and medicine. Only after this transaction had taken place did I set the giant badgers onto him.

Not long after this incident, Mr Bewg announced that he had found himself another job, and wished to terminate his contract of employment. If his inane burbling was to be believed, he had been offered the post of Assistant Slave at a charnel-house, the main duties being to crawl on his hands and knees in foul pits of ordure. While I listened patiently, he explained that he felt this post would give him opportunities undreamed of in his current position, and that he was prepared to take a cut in salary in order to take up the offer. Poking at him with a stick, I nodded my consent. I had no wish to stand in his way. My only concern was that he would have the common decency to fulfil the terms and conditions of his contract before setting off for greener pastures. I then reminded him of the form he had signed on his first day at the factory, the main clauses of which stated that in order to leave, he was required to give forty years notice and to repay every single penny of his salary since day one. To my surprise, Mr Bewg—who moments before had been adamant that he wanted to leave—now said that he would like a few more days to consider the matter. Once again I nodded my assent, then summoned fourteen of my assistants, who bundled Mr Bewg out of my office and set him to work on his latest task, which was to lie face down in a muddy ditch while a herd of demented bison charged over him.

In view of the above, I must admit that I cannot in truth recommend Mr Bewg to you. His work is shoddy, his attendance and punctuality leave much to be desired, and I have the gravest doubts about his character. His sickness record is thoroughly unsatisfactory, and I have been put in the uncomfortable position of having to threaten various members of the medical profession with monstrous violence after they had the temerity to issue Mr Bewg with certificates recommending that he stay off work for half an hour. However, should you decide to ignore my warnings and offer a job to Mr Bewg, I will have great pleasure in delivering what is left of him to your premises upon the expiry of his notice period in forty years time.

Yours sincerely
B. Git

Back to stories

About Belt, Bong And Yaw

Monday

Red huts on the horizon stank of steam. Yaw's boil made Belt more hollow. He went towards the lighthouse with paint from the hotels. Bong spoke of coastguards, anvils, butter and Yaw. Belt felt sick. Bong stank of starch. Yaw had his wax. He broke up in the potters.

Wednesday

Wallets'd got Bong all worn out. Belt's more furtive. He's got lawns. Yaw caught a fever. Bong yelped. Wellington boots pained him. Yaw was floored. Belt took a closer look. Things looked black. Bong had gravy in his sack. Some of Yaw's netting took Bong aback. He kept on mentioning Belt behind his back. Yaw was careful with his spoon. Belt went to the kennels. Bong rang a bell. He threw up in his dinner. That made Yaw gawp. He curled up by the sails. They put Bong in prison. He was all tucked up. Yaw wrote a letter to his mother. Belt was in the pantry helping Bong make butter.

Thursday

Logging in Idaho, Yaw found some bones. Those bones were Bong's bones. Belt's matron ate his brie. Yaw muttered. He fell about in fits. At the waterworks, Belt broke corks. His elk was in a tent. It looked like Bong. Bread rolls and snacks were stacked in crates. Yaw put them by his flask. He threw up on some rudders.

Saturday

Bong's belt made Belt choke. Yaw coughed blood. Hooks in Bong's bungalow looked like claws. But Belt kept calm. Yaw disembarked from a barge. His harbour was red. Belt's blue. He struck a match.Bong bent down. His coat was torn. His gun was sunk. Belt's pottery had to be glued. But Yaw's was hard. It looked like wood. Bong had said it would. Bong stank. But Belt had better irons. They raged. Bong's grew. Yaw had no irons in the fire. He kept them in his lockers.

Back to stories

Hooting Yard Projects

The Translation Project

The story “Some Ponds, A Hotel, The Hollyhocks” has been translated from English into Serbo-Croat. This is the first step of the project. The next stage is for the Serbo-Croat text to be translated into, say, French, the French into Urdu, the Urdu into Finnish, the Finnish into Chinese… and so on, until, dozens (or hundreds) of languages later, the text is translated back into English. If you are able to translate from Serbo-Croat into a language other than English, please leave a message with your old friend the Duty Git.

The Ice Project

Plans are afoot for the Hooting Yard Ice Archive. The idea is to compile a ludicrously exhaustive library of information about ice. From the ice cubes in a freezer to the wind-blasted wastes of Antarctica—if you have any information about ice, or know of any existing ice archives which can be subsumed into the Hooting Yard archive, let the Ice Archivist know.

The Homunculus Project

This project is code-named Homunculus for reasons so abstruse that not even people skilled in deciphering immensely abstruse things can work it out. The project is meant to work as follows:

You have visited Hooting Yard and have got this far.
You are sufficiently interested to want to contribute to the Homunculus Project.
You are willing to help define what the Homunculus Project should include, and what it should exclude.
You are prepared, if necessary, to devote the rest of your life to the Homunculus Project.
You understand that the Homunculus Project is self-generating, and no one is in charge.

Send your ideas to The Homunculus Project.

Some possible starting points: Tristram Shandy, the history of lighthouses, Oulipo, obscure farm implements, things that vanish, Muggletonians… As the project develops, progress updates will appear on the Hooting Yard Site and/or be posted to contributors.

The CCC Project

“CCC” stands for “Cryptic Crossword Clue”. You are invited to send in either:

Texts composed entirely from (genuine) cryptic crossword clues, or
Single clues which can be used by others to compose texts.

If possible, please give the source: publication, date, setter (if known), etc. Send your clues to the Tetchy Cruciverbist.

Projects Update

Here are some highlights from the responses to the various projects. Let me rewrite that. Here are all of the responses to the various projects:

Cam Baddeley writes:

I firmly believe that the Homunculus Project should exclude any reference to gases. Liquids, yes. Gases, no. I am keenly interested in things which, when left alone for long periods, may or may not turn into something else, eg my grandfather's tools, which have been in a large chest in my father's garage for twenty years, or the correspondence Edward Gorey admits to having left unopened for thirty-five years. I am unconvinced that the contents of either of these are the same contents that were originally lodged, and defy anyone to conclusively prove otherwise. I can see the Melbourne docks, the country rail yards and several fairly substantial chimneys from my office window. If I could see a gasometer I would be the happiest man on earth.

C.J. Baddeley cbaddeley@infoxchange.net.au

I think Cam has hit the nail on the head there. But which nail? And whose head? Meanwhile, Tempel Ov Spoon has (have?) been very forthcoming on ice topics. First, on pykrete:

From Pyke—The Unknown Genius, by David Lampe: “Pyke had conceived of the Plough project to solve a few specific problems of the war, but his Habbakuk idea, he felt, would do much more. It would solve all the war's problems—as well as those problems of the peace which would follow. The three elements of the scheme were to be ice, sawdust and very cold water. Pure ice, Pyke had learned, is molecularly very similarly to pure concrete, although it has an even lower temsile strength. If however, small particles of some other substance are suspended in water, and if that water is frozen, the reinforced ice has remarkable qualities. The reinforcement boosts the ice's tensile strenghth tremendously. Pyke had learned that particles of wood—such as the chips used in paper manufacture—can micro-reinforce ice very much.

“The memo then pointed to a certain little-known characteristic of super-cooled water—water chilled below freezing-point but not allowed to congeal. In a pre-war study made by the United States Bureau of Standards, research indicated that, contrary to popular teaching, such water need not be kept static.

“In the Brooklyn Polytechnic's Cold Research Laboratories scientists working for Pyke had added between four and fourteen per cent of wood pulp to water. The slush thus produced was frozen into a material at first named piccolite and later called pykrete. Initial tests of the material gave fantastic results.

“The crush resistance of clear ice is between 250 and 1,300 pounds per square inch, but pykrete's crush resistance proved to be more than 3,000 pounds per square inch. A one inch column of pykrete was found to be strong enough to support the weight of a medium-sized motorcar quite easily. The wood pulp insulated pykerete quite remarkably after the material's outer surface thawed, making it considerably more stable at high temperatures than ordinary ice. A relatively small expenditure of energy would keep it frozen.

“Pyke's Habbakuk memorandum went on to make some very incredible suggestions. Why not build giant aircraft carriers entirely of pykerete—ships two thousand feet long with thirty-foot-thick hulls? Since pykeretes specific gravity is lower than that of ice, the ships would be unsinkable. The maximum speed need only be seven knots, he estimated, but because of pykerete's invulnerability this would not matter. Initial scientific calculation suggested that if hit broadside by a torpedo, the carrier hulls would suffer a crater only three feet deep and about twenty feet in diameter. Such hulls could resist waves a hundred feet high, and incendiary attack woulkd hardly damage them.

“Pykrete carriers' hollowed hulls would contain freezing plants, workshops, airplane hangars and living quarters—all as snugly warm as igloos. Their runways would launch any military aircraft then in use. Each iceberg aircraft carrier would contain sufficient deisel fuel in its tanks for seven-thousand-mile non-stop cruises. Freezing units would circulate cold air throughout cardboard tubes, frozen vein-like into the pykrete kulls, to allow ships to withstand the most torrid weather, and cork sheathing would preserve the hulls' exterior contours against the effects of possible evaporation.

“Pyke's memo then suggested pykrete freighters, each so large that it would carry as much cargo as eighty Liberty ships! Rather than be unloaded with cranes (obviously inefficient, Pyke remarked), holes would be carved in the sides of the ice freighters and cargo would then be slid off onto ice barges (these to be built for only $200 apiece, according to Pyke's calculations). The freighter's sides could then be frozen shut again quite easily. Their usefulness outlived, the iceberg freighters would be taken to open water and allowed to melt. The memo also suggested a large pykrete carrier, four thousand feet long, as well as smaller berg ships.”

As if that weren't enough, Tempel added the following:

Pyke managed to stretch the boundaries of eccentricity and would brief members of the War Cabinet from his bed whilst surrounded by beer bottles full of piss, because going to the lavatory would waste time that he could otherwise use by working on his inventions.

Another ice story you might like to pick up on is that one of the ice mummies of the Incas, Sarita, has just been discovered in the Andes. For more details go to: http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/nova/peru/

spooky@mail.bogo.co.uk (TempelOvSpoon)

Marvellous stuff. This is precisely the sort of thing to keep shovelling in to the Ice Archive until all known hard disk space in the world is frozen solid with it. More ice from Jonathan Edmondston:

Interesting facts about Ice:

It only exists at negative temperatures, unless you are using the Fahrenheit or Reameur(?) scales, or you are in another dimension
Most of the planet Pluto is ice
If all the ice on earth melted at once, the planet would be flooded, and you wouldn't be able to have scotch on the rocks
Penguins walk on ice, but Mars bars slide
Rod, Jane and Freddy (of Rainbow fame) once sang a song about ‘Coconut ice tasting very nice’
The Ice Warriors on Doctor Who were the only alien race who actually looked different to each other, unlike the daleks, cybermen, etc.
In the anti-matter universe, ice would solidify into water, and water-bergs would float on the ice seas, causing a danger to shipping everywhere (especially Portsmouth harbour)

Edmondston@dial.pipex.com

Thank you for that, Jonathan—especially number 6, which could lead to a project of its own if anyone has further thoughts on such things. Finally, a rather ambitious scheme for the Homunculus Project from Tim Drage:

Idea: Locate the plant/insect which most resembles a human being, and selectively breed it until undistinguisiable from the real thing.

tim@drage.demon.co.uk

Well, yes, Tim, but when are we going to find the time? You can visit Tim at http://www.yi.com/home/DrageTim/ (unless he's too busy carrying out demented experiments in his lab, as his cackling factotum Mungo drags in another sack of insects…)

You'd better go back to the Home Page, unless you want to look at Planet of the Severe Haircuts